A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 9287-11774 FA739D
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 9287-11774
1936-2005
1950s-1990s
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA739D
54.72 Cubic Feet Document boxes 385-529.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Catalogued Reports are open for research with select reports restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Other Finding Aids
For descriptions of Ford Foundation Catalogued Reports, please refer to the following finding aids (arranged by Report Number):
FA739A Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 1-3254
FA739B Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 3255-6261
FA739C Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 6262-9286
FA739E Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 11775-13948
FA739F Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 13949-17726
FA739G Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 17727-19980
Arrangement
The Catalogued Reports are arranged numerically by an arbitrary call number assigned during cataloging, from 1 to approximately 20,000.
Biographical / Historical
In the early 1970s, the Ford Foundation's archives staff began to identify and catalog individual reports, policy and programming documents, and program evaluations in an effort to create an internal lending-library of useful documents. Many of the Catalogued Reports were physically culled from the former Foundation officers' and staff's archival collections of 'office files'. When those collections of 'office files' were later processed, and finding aids created, an appendix of "Reports Removed" (or, Reports Transferred") was added to the finding aids.
By 1977 the collection included more than 3,500 reports, and by 1979 some 5,000 reports had been cataloged.
Duplicated copies of the reports were also created on microfiche, and later microfilm.
Scope and Contents
The Ford Foundation's Catalogued Reports collection includes policy and programming documents, program evaluations, and periodic program status reports produced by Foundation officers and staff, as well as consultants and grantees. Some published material produced by Ford Foundation grants is also included in the collection. The collection also includes some of the Ford Foundation's own publications, such as the Annual Reports and newsletters.
- The Ford Foundation in the United Arab Republic: information for program specialists and staff (Reports 009287), 1965 (Box 385)
  Program Name
  Overseas Division/Near East and Africa
  Extent
  38 leaves: tables -- 28 cm.
  Consultants -- Egypt -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Technical assistance -- Egypt; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States -- Personnel management; Endowments -- Egypt -- Evaluation
- The Ford Foundation in the United Arab Republic (Reports 009288), 1970; Ivy, James T. (Box 385)
  Abstract/Summary
  "A report prepared for Mr. Abdel Moneim El-Naggar, Ministry of Foreign Affairs." --T.p.
  International Division/Middle East and Africa
  1 v.;var. pag. -- 28 cm.
  Endowments -- Egypt -- Evaluation; Technical assistance -- Egypt
- Report on the mission to the Sudan, March 19-22 (Reports 009289), 1973; Billeh, Victor; Za'rour, George I. (Box 385)
  12 p.
  The Sudan -- Education
- Administrative policies and procedures (Reports 009290), 1969; Stucky, Conrad C. (Box 385)
  Related Grant Number
  06290135
  Related Grantee Name
  Foundation-Administered Project (FAP)
  Related Grant Purpose
  Program specialists and consultants for public administration in Saudi Arabia.
  37 p. -- 28 cm.
  Public administration -- Saudi Arabia; Technical assistance -- Saudi Arabia
- Library handbook (Reports 009291), 1973 (Box 385)
  Administration/Library
  40 p.
  Library administration -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.
- Original report of Iverson-Moyer et al mission --Near East, 1951 or 1952. (Reports 009292) (Box 385)
  Overseas Division
  100 p.
  Economic development -- Middle East; Education, Higher -- Middle East; Vocational education -- Middle East; Rural development -- Middle East
- Administrative policies and procedures applicable to Ford Foundation professional staff in the U.A.R. (Reports 009293), 1969; Ivy, James T. (Box 385)
  32 leaves + appendices -- 28 cm.
  Consultants -- Egypt -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Technical assistance -- Egypt
- Notes on T. Keenen reporting trip (Oct. 17, 1962-January 8, 1963): The Middle East (Reports 009294), Keenan, Terrance (Box 385)
  various pagings.
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- Middle East
- Terminal evaluation: National School of Administration, Algeria (Reports 009295), 1974; Roberts, Richard S., 1935- (Box 386)
  Memo to Robert H. Edwards and Wilbert J. LeMelle, dated April 18, 1974.
  4 leaves -- 28 cm.
  Public administration -- Study and teaching -- Algeria; Civil service -- Study and teaching -- Algeria; Technical assistance -- Algeria; Endowments -- Algeria -- Evaluation
- Terminal evaluation: secretarial and accountancy schools, Algeria (Reports 009296), 1974; Roberts, Richard S., 1935- (Box 386)
  Memo to Robert H. Edwards and Wilbert J. LeMelle, dated April 11, 1974.
  5 leaves -- 28 cm.
  Accounting -- Study and teaching -- Algeria; Public administration -- Study and teaching -- Algeria; Technical assistance -- Algeria; Endowments -- Algeria -- Evaluation
- Terminal evaluation: english language textbook development for secondary schools, Tunisia, (690-0742) (Reports 009297), 1974; Roberts, Richard S., 1935- (Box 386)
  Memo to Robert H. Edwards and Wilbert J. LeMelle, dated April 30, 1974.
  06900742
  Republic of Tunisia
  English language textbook development for secondary schools.
  English language -- Study and teaching -- Tunisia -- Textbooks; English teachers -- Training of -- Tunisia
- Background to delegated authority grant to CAFRAD (Reports 009298), 1974; Roberts, Richard S., 1935- (Box 386)
  6 p.
  African Training and Research Centre in Administration for Development; African Training and Research Centre In Administration for Development
- Environmental development in the Middle East (Reports 009299), 1974; Olson, Thomas F., 1940- (Box 386)
  11 leaves: table -- 28 cm.
  Science -- Research -- Lebanon; Agriculture -- Research -- Lebanon; Industrialization -- Lebanon; Majlis al-Waṭanī lil-Buḥūth al-ʻIlmīyah (Lebanon)
- Thoughts on the character and objective of English language projects in the Middle East and Africa Program (Reports 009300), 1966; Hall, Harvey (Box 386)
  5 p.
  English language training -- Middle East; English language training -- Africa
- The Arid Lands Agricultural Program, outlook and planning review, observations, implications and suggestions (Reports 009301), 1971 (Box 386)
  28 p.
  Agriculture -- Middle East; Agriculture -- Africa, North
- A program for economic and social development of the Caspian-Mazandaran region of Iran: a discussion paper (Reports 009302), 1963; Hill, Rey M. (Box 386)
  18 leaves + attachments: tables -- 28 cm.
  Central planning -- Iran; Economic development -- Iran; Social planning -- Iran; Rural development -- Iran; Technical assistance -- Iran
- The Ford Foundation program in North Africa: 1961-1971 (Reports 009303), Wortham, Anne, 1941- (Box 386)
  [v], 25 leaves + appendices -- 28 cm.
  Technical assistance -- Africa, North; Endowments -- Africa, North -- Evaluation
- Safeguarding human rights in Biomedical research (Reports 009304), 1972 (Box 386)
  International Division/Population Program
  L72-136.
  3 p.
  Ford Foundation Series
  Ford Foundation funded research involving human subjects
  Medicine -- Research -- Human rights; Human rights -- Biomedical research
- Implementation of policy statement regarding biomedical research involving patients and volunteers (Reports 009305), 1974; Speir, Robert W. (Box 386)
  3 p. + appendices.
- The Ford Foundation and the WHO expanded program of research, development and research training in human reproduction (Reports 009306), 1972; Perkin, Gordon W. (Box 386)
  International Division/Latin America and the Caribbean
  Population; World Health Organization; WHO Ford Foundation.
- Problems in introducing an evaluation system: the Jamaica experience (Reports 009307), 1970; Trowbridge, James W. (Box 386)
  9 leaves -- 28 cm.
  Birth control -- Jamaica; Jamaica. National Family Planning Board
- Recommendations to the Director, Dr. Lenworth Jacobs, M.D. National Family Planning Board, Kingston 5, Jamaica, resulting from visit of May 10-18 (Reports 009308), 1969; Ebanks, G. E. (Box 386)
  14 p.
- Observations and recommendations based on my visit to the National Family Planning Board, Kingston, Jamaica over the period September 24-30 (Reports 009309), 1969; Ebanks, G. E. (Box 386)
  8 p.
  Birth control clinics -- Jamaica; Jamaica. National Family Planning Board
- Report on consultantship with National Family Planning Board (NFPB), Jamaica, December 30, 1968-January 3 (Reports 009310), 1969; Ebanks, G. E. (Box 386)
  4 p.
- Report and recommendations to the Director the National Family Planning Board, period of visit: December 30, 1968-January 3 (Reports 009311), 1969; Ebanks, G. E. (Box 386)
  7 p.
- A Seminar on Socio-Economic Research and Training in Agriculture: program and background papers (Reports 009312), 1973; Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (Box 386)
  Seminar sponsored by the Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research at the World Bank, Washington DC. July 27-28, 1973.
  75 p.
  Agriculture; Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research
- Formal and nonformal education in educational development: Some issues examined Princeton University (Reports 009313), 1974; Swett M., Francisco X. (Box 386)
  International Division/Latin America and the Caribbean;International Division/Latin America and the Caribbean
  93 p.
  Education -- Latin America
- Higher education, science and technology in Mexico's economic development: a preliminary study (Reports 009314), 1966; Urquidi, Victor L.; Lajous Vargas, Adrián; Colegio de Mexico (Box 386)
  International Division/Latin America
  104 leaves: tables -- 28 cm.
  Science -- Research -- Mexico; Technology -- Research -- Mexico; Education, Higher -- Mexico; Economic development -- Mexico; Social planning -- Mexico; Colegio de Mexico
- A review of the Ford Foundation's child care assistance policy (Reports 009315), 1980; Probst, Annice M. (Box 386)
  Women's Programs/Operations and Management/Personnel
  78 p.
  Child care -- Policy
- Communicating with communicators: a study of the International Institute of Communications (Reports 009316), 1979; Straus, Richard (Box 386)
  Office of Communications/International Division/European and International Affairs
  07400019
  44 p. + annex.
  Communication; International Institute of Communications
- Evaluation of Ford Foundation Grant PA64-434 to the Center for Research on Economic Development, University of Michigan, 1967-1980 (Reports 009317), 1982; Stremlau, Carolyn C. (Box 386)
  International Division/Middle East and Africa/Developing Countries Program/West Africa
  06400434
  Regents of the University of Michigan
  Strengthening the Center for Research on Economic Development.
  36 p. + attachments: tables -- 28 cm.
  Economics -- Research -- Africa, West; Economics -- Study and teaching -- Africa, West; Endowments -- United States -- Evaluation; University of Michigan. Center for Research on Economic Development
- CRED (Recommendations), Resource Bases and Recruitment (Suggestions) (Reports 009318), 1968; Lewis, Ben W. (Ben William), 1900-1987 (Box 386)
  Resource bases -- Middle East and Asia
- Evaluation of research produced during the year 1977-78 by CEUR-Buenos Aires (Reports 009319), 1978; Willig, Richard L. (Box 386)
  International Division/Developing Countries Program
  07700525
  25 p.
  City planning; Regional planning; Center for Studies of the State and Society (CEDES)
- Observations on the Indonesian cultural scene (Reports 009320), 1977; Lyons, Elizabeth (Box 386)
  International Division/Asia and the Pacific
  73-805.
  13 p. + attachments.
  Arts -- Indonesia; Cultural preservation -- Indonesia
- Report on my visit to Palembang to evaluate the Population Education Course for SLA teachers, Feb. 22 and 23 (Reports 009321), 1974; Jones, Gavin W.; McDonald, Peter (Box 386)
  Developing Countries Program/Asia and the Pacific
  07450301
  Education -- Population; Education, Higher -- Indonesia
- Assessment of the Documentation of the association of African Universities (AAU) (Reports 009322), 1974; Lange, K. J. (Karl Julius), 1755-1813 (Box 386)
  07200020
  13 p.
  Education, Higher -- Africa; Documentation centres -- Africa
- Report on the Documentation Centre on the AAU in ACCRA based on Travel in Paris and West Africa Feb. 2-28 (Reports 009323), 1974; Panofsky, Hans E. (Box 386)
  2 p.
- A picture of the population problem in Brazil today (Reports 009324), 1966; Almeida, Ivàn (Box 386)
  06600124
  Federal University of Bahia
  23 p. + attachments.
  Population research -- Brazil; Universidade Federal da Bahia
- Report on trip to Bahia (Reports 009325), 1965; Carlson, Reynold E. (Reynold Erland) (Box 386)
  File memo dated June 26, 1965.
  International Division/Office of the Vice President
  Program in reproductive biology and fertility control at the University.
  8 leaves -- 28 cm.
  Birth control clinics -- Brazil -- Evaluation; Human reproduction -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Brazil; Population assistance -- Brazil; Birth control -- Brazil; Education, Higher -- Brazil; Universities and colleges -- Brazil; Bahia, Brazil (State). Universidad Federal
- Site visit to Federal University of Bahia (Reports 009326), 1974; Southam, Anna L., 1915- (Box 386)
  File memo dated October 24, 1974.
  6 leaves + attachment
  Human reproduction -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Brazil; Universities and colleges -- Brazil; Population assistance -- Brazil; Birth control -- Brazil; Education, Higher -- Brazil; Bahia, Brazil (State). Universidad Federal
- Puebla Project - An analysis of benefits and costs (Reports 009327), 1971; Winkelmann, Donald (Box 387)
  06700204
  Agricultural development projects -- Research institutes; Puebla Project Mexico
- Memorandum: financing international agricultural research institutes (Reports 009328), 1968; Hill, F. F. (Forrest Frank) (Box 387)
  15 p. + attachments.
  Agricultural development projects; Agriculture -- International cooperation; Agricultural research institutes
- Trip to Southeast Asia (Reports 009329), 1967; Lonnquist, J. H. (Box 387)
  Agriculture -- Internationl development; Agricultural research institutes
- Visit to Department of Agricultural Economics, UFCe, April 12 (Reports 009330), 1978; Saint, William Staver, 1944- (Box 387)
  06900731
  20 p.
  Agriculture -- Economic aspects -- Brazil; Agriculture -- Economic aspects -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Brazil; Federal University of Ceara. Dept. of Agricultural Economics.
- Progress and problems of the Master's Degree Program in Agricultural Economics of the Federal University of Ceara (Reports 009331), 1976; Sanders, J. H. (John Howard) (Box 387)
  Title sufficient as abstract.
  Latin America and the Caribbean/Brazil
  Federal University of Ceara
  30 p.
  Agriculture -- Economic aspects -- Study and teaching (Graduate) -- Brazil; Federal University of Ceara. Dept. of Agricultural Economics.
- Selecting and evaluating new technology for small farmers in the Central Sertao of Ceara (Reports 009332), 1971; Lima, Dalmo Marcelo de Albuquerque; Sanders, J. H. (John Howard) (Box 387)
  27 p.
  Agriculture -- Economic aspects -- Brazil; Farms, Small -- Brazil
- Review of Benin Grant, Francophone Students at Ibadan (Reports 009333), 1976; Elliott, Howard (Box 387)
  07500435
  Education, Higher -- Benin; Agriculture -- Benin
- Evaluation of Grant to the National University of Nenin in support of Study and Research Program for Beninois students at the University of Ibandan and IITA (Reports 009334), 1978; Elliott, Howard (Box 387)
  Education, Higher -- Benin
- Report of Consultant, Dr. Assa Ayemou, on visit to University of Benin and Evaluation of the Benin Ibandan - IITA Program (Reports 009335), 1978; Elliott, Howard (Box 387)
  16 p.
- Advanced International Reporting Fellows Columbia University Graduate School of Journalism: Ford Foundation Seminar February 22-23, 1971. (Reports 009336) (Box 387)
  Includes list: Alumni of the Advanced International Reporting Program, Graduate School of Journalism, Columbia University.
  International Division
  19 p.
  Ford Foundation activities
- Problems of urbanization in Kingston, Jamaica (Reports 009337), 1971; Trowbridge, James W. (Box 387)
  Urbanization -- Jamaica; Poor -- Jamaica
- Observations on the situation in Pakistan (Reports 009338), 1971; Staples, Eugene S. (Box 387)
  13 leaves -- 28 cm.
  Technical assistance -- Pakistan; Technical assistance -- Bangladesh; Endowments -- Pakistan -- Evaluation; Endowments -- Bangladesh -- Evaluation
- Pakistan: Mid- (Reports 009339), 1971; Staples, Eugene S. (Box 387)
  3 leaves -- 28 cm.
- Social Science Program, Fiscal Year 1969 Budget (Reports 009340), 1968; Silvert, Kalman H. (Box 387)
  Related Conference
  PAPER Conference (1968 Nov. 6-8: Bogota, Colombia)
  Agricultural development projects -- Latin America
- An annotated bibliography on the history of American Foundations (Reports 009341), 1984; McCarthy, Kathleen D. (Box 387)
  Office of the Vice President
  1 v. v(arious pagings) -- 28 cm.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted from scholarly access.
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States -- History; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States -- Bibliography; Charities -- United States -- History; Charities -- United States -- Bibliography; Nonprofit organizations -- United States
- Potential for Foundation support to the Fundacion Promotora de Cooperativas (FPC) and the Universidad Centro Americana Jose Simeon Canas (UCA) in El Salvador (Reports 009342), 1974; Schuman, Barry; Nelson, Michael. (Box 387)
  18 p.
  Rural development -- Central America
- Trip to Costa Rica and Guatemala (Reports 009343), 1971; Funari, John (Box 387)
  11 leaves -- 28 cm.
  Technical assistance -- Costa Rica; Technical assistance -- Guatemala
- Tentative outline for discussions, meetings of Central American urban and regional planners and observers, to be sponsored by the Ford Foundation (Reports 009344), 1968; Martin, Marshall A. (Box 387)
  City planning -- Central America; Cities and towns -- Central America
- Palabras explicativas por el arquitecto Mario Martin de Honduras (Reports 009345), 1968; Martin, Marshall A. (Box 387)
  36 p.
  Seminar: urban and regional development (San Salvador)
- After one-quarter of a century: An evaluation of the Institute of Social and Economic Research, the University of the West Indies (Reports 009346), 1975; Freeman, Howard E.; Brewster, Havelock; Milne, R. S. (Robert Stephen), 1919-; Onitiri, H. M. A.; Reeder, Leo G. (Box 387)
  Draft, May 1974, copy included.
  65 p.
  Social and economic research; University of the West Indies
- Consultative Group for International Agricultural Research (Reports 009347), 1971; Bell, David E., 1919-2000
  Memo to Heads, POICs and overseas representatives, dated May 24, 1971.
  2 p. + attachments -- 28 cm.
  Agriculture -- Research -- Developing countries; Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research
- Stiftung Volkswagenwerk (The Volkswagen Foundation) (Reports 009348), 1971; Bader, William B. (Box 387)
  International Division/European and International Affairs
  Foundations -- Europe
- Program strategy in Central America: science and technology (Reports 009349), 1968; Banks, Robert, 1922-2002 (Box 387)
  Memo to Messrs. Gamble, Bergman, Blair, Coonty, Gonzales, Rubel, Stevenson, Veneaian, and Miss Tanck, August 21, 1968.
  10 leaves -- 28 cm.
  Science -- Study and teaching (Graduate) -- Central America; Engineering -- Study and teaching (Graduate) -- Research -- Central America; Education (Graduate) -- Central America
- Universidad Metropolitana Caracas (Reports 009350), 1972; Banks, Robert, 1922-2002 (Box 387)
  Education, Higher -- Venezuela; Universidad Metropolitana (Caracas, Venezuela)
- Social sciences program strategy for Central America (Reports 009351), 1968; Blair, Calvin P. (Box 387)
  Social sciences -- Central America
- YORUBA Six-year Project: The June 1976 evaluation: McGill Univ (Reports 009352), Cziko, Gary A. (Gary Andrew); Ojerinde, Adedibu, 1949- (Box 387)
  07000159
  34 p. + appendix.
  Education, Primary -- Nigeria
- YORUBA Six-Year Project: The June 1977 evaluation: McGill Univ (Reports 009353), 1978; Cziko, Gary A. (Gary Andrew); Ojerinde, Adedibu, 1949- (Box 387)
- Adlai E. Stevenson Institute (Reports 009354), 1975; Heaps, David; Unviersity of Chicago (Box 387)
  United States and International Affairs Program/International Affairs
  07600022
  The Greater Washington Educational Telecommunications Association, Inc.
  Support of management reorganization and national programming.
  15 leaves + attachment -- 28 cm.
  International affairs -- Study and teaching; Adlai Stevenson Institute of International Affairs
- Humanities, humanists, and values (Reports 009355), 1977; Sharpe, Richard S. (Box 387)
  Education and Research/Public Policy and Social Organization
  10 p. + attachments.
  Humanities -- Foundation work
- Informe del Viaje del Lic. Rodrigo A. Medellin, Al Indide: Ciudad de Lima, del 26 de Febrero al 10 de Marzo de (Reports 009356), 1973; Medellín, Rodrigo A. (Box 387)
  07100569
  Education -- Research -- Peru; INDIDE.
- Informe del Doctor Pablo Latapi Sobre las Actividades de Investigacion en el INIPM (Reports 009357), 1972; Latapí, Pablo (Box 387)
  15 p. + appendix.
  Education -- Research -- Peru; INIPM
- Consultation re a proposed program of assistance to the MED Educational Research Center: University of Pittsburgh (Reports 009358), 1971; Paulston, Rolland G. (Box 387)
  Education -- Research -- Peru; MED. Educational Research Center
- The Overseas Development Council: an evaluation for the Ford and Rockefeller Foundations, 1982 (Reports 009359), Gwin, Catherine; Moose, Richard M.; Overseas Development Council (Box 387)
  08000461;07900373.
  68 leaves.
  Economic assistance, American -- Developing countries; Overseas Development Council
- An evaluation of the accelerated cereal projects in Tunisia and in Algeria and the related Ford Foundation grants to CIMMYT (Reports 009360), 1973; Bronzi, Piero (Box 388)
  PA68-848
  44 p. -- 28 cm.
  Agricultural development projects -- Africa, North; Cereal products -- Agriculture -- Africa, North; Agriculture -- Africa, North; Accelerated Cereal Production Project
- Brazil Northeast Research Project: Program of Development of Resource Research center for the Semi-Arid Zone (Reports 009361), 1975; Ryan, J. G. (James G.) (Box 388)
  07300725
  Institute of Agronomic Research
  Agricultural development projects -- Brazil; Institute of Agronomic Research (Cameroon)
- Brazil Northeast Research Project: Program for Sorghum/Millet research (Reports 009362), 1975; Ryan, J. G. (James G.) (Box 388)
  09350725
  10 p.
  Agricultural development projects -- Brazil
- Terminal report on the Ford Foundation agricultural production technology project on Sorghum and Millets for the Semi-Arid Region of Northeast Brazil (Reports 009363), 1978; Faris, Mohamed A. (Box 388)
- Proposed approaches to programming on ethnic conflict (Reports 009365), undated (Box 388)